Part 1: What is mucositis?
Radiation works mostly on rapidly dividing
cells.
Your tumor is rapidly
dividing and growing,
and we want radiation to kill the tumor.
However,
your mucosal membranes are also rapidly
dividing.
As cells are secreting fluids
to line your mouth and throat.
These cells are sensitive to radiation
and can become inflamed
or irritated during radiation.
This is mucositis.
Mucositis, may first appear
as red as tender tissue
along your tongue,
back of your mouth, and throat.
If it worsens, you may notice
some white spots or ulcers along
the tongue, cheek, or throat.
They likely will be painful
and sensitive to touch.
Sometimes you can see them yourself by
shining light and looking into the mirror.
Your doctor will also examine you weekly
during treatment to look for mucositis.